<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Expedient for peace amongst Christians. The second part grounded on the impossibility of their agreement in matters of religion : and further enlarged in a discourse of church and state : wherein a new ecclesiastical administration is exhibited.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39064</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3872A_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R31481</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12002146</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12002146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52247</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39064)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52247)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1009:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Expedient for peace amongst Christians. The second part grounded on the impossibility of their agreement in matters of religion : and further enlarged in a discourse of church and state : wherein a new ecclesiastical administration is exhibited.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and sold by George Larkin ... and R. Janeway ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52247:1"/>
            <p>An Expedient for Peace amongſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>The SECOND PART.</p>
            <p>GROUNDED On the Impoſſibility of their Agreement in Matters of Religion.</p>
            <p>And further Enlarged in a DISCOURSE OF Church and State.</p>
            <p>WHEREIN A <hi>New Eccleſiaſtical Administration</hi> is Exhibited</p>
            <q>Behold I will bring it Health and Cure, and I will Cure them, and I will <hi>Reveal</hi> unto them the abundance of <hi>PEACE</hi> and <hi>TRUTH.</hi> And I will cauſe the Captivity of <hi>Judah,</hi> and the Captivity of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to return, and I will build them as at the firſt. <bibl>Jer, 33. v. 6.7.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed and Sold by <hi>George Larkin</hi> at the <hi>Two Swans</hi> without <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopſgate,</hi> and <hi>R. Janeway</hi> in <hi>Queens-Head-Alley</hi> in <hi>Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſter-Row.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:52247:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52247:2"/>
            <head>EPISTOLA DEDICATORIA.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>TEmpus refrigerationis è conſpectu Domini dequo Locutus eſt Deus pér os omnium Sanctorum Prophetarum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventum eſt.</hi> Judaeis ergò Gentilibuſque; cunctis <hi>Pacis</hi> &amp; <hi>Justitiae</hi> Cultoribus, Nec non omnibus Hujus mundi faelicem Statum, Gloriam Dei, aut Regnum Chriſti, ex corde cupientibus, Author hoc opuſculum primariò De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicat, horum omnium cupientiſſimus. Deindè Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canae Conventioni Auguſtiſſimae.</p>
            <p>Coetus Honorabilis! Naufragium Eccleſiae accidiſſe, Partes laceratae in mudani oceani faciem uſquequaquè diffluentes ſatìs demonſtrant, &amp; divinâ Providentiâ eſt penès vos reparare, &amp; irrefragabilem reddere in aeternum. Eſt igitur inquirendum quâ rupe, queis ſcopulis frangeba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Tum ad iſtam partem, quae ad vos (Patres Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripti!) ſpectat, datâ veniâ, ego abſolvam, <hi>viz:</hi> San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cire leges in Religione, non eſt ſancire Religionem, ſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere; eſt dare Veniam peccantibus, &amp; Sectas &amp; Diviſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes creare, ut hodiè planè conſtat. De quibus tunc verſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur <hi>Lex?</hi> Dicam, <hi>Leges</hi> in favorem Societatum, Artium, mutuorum Foederum, &amp; Commercij ferendae ſunto. Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio eſt Dei Provincia Peculiaris, de illâ ad ferendas Leges
<pb facs="tcp:52247:3"/>miſit filium, &amp; exhibuit Sacras Literas, &amp; de his Legibus ipſe <hi>ſolus</hi> eſt Judex &amp; Veritas <hi>ſola</hi> Regula, quam <hi>Lex</hi> creare nullo modo poteſt. Quid igitur vobis agendum eſt? Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequendum Chriſti praecepto, qui Dixit <hi>Ite &amp; Docete,</hi> &amp;c. Ille hìc principto primas exhibuit lineas, &amp; Primum Ecle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia Saxum poſuit quod reſpuebant Aedificatores fatui, ſed vos penès eſt anguli <hi>Capitale</hi> redere. Oh Gloria! Quae lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, qui honores Veſtras circumſtant ſedes? Quàm hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabile erit in Secula Seculorum, inter omnes Gentes &amp; Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarum orbis incolas, <hi>Pacis &amp; Juſtitia</hi> Fundatores, &amp; Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae tum Judaeis tum Gentilibus Reſtauratores appellari? Pergite igitur ſub Beatis Auſpicijs Regis <hi>Pacis</hi> &amp; <hi>Veritatis,</hi> Domini noſtri Jeſu Chriſti.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52247:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Will not Affront thee ſo much, as to ſuppoſe thee ignorant of the great Stir and Noiſe made in the World about Religion; For this would ſuppoſe thee to want thy Sences: But if thou contributeſt to raiſe the Duſt, if thou art one of thoſe <hi>Bigots,</hi> thoſe tenacious Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mals, that will not part with their very Excrements, the cuttings of thy Hair, or the paring of thy Nails, for the <hi>Publick Peace,</hi> I charge thee to lay down my Book <hi>(Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe my Courtſhip)</hi> for I had rather thou wouldſt tear, than read it.</p>
            <p>'Tis to free and ingenuous Minds, diveſted of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices, who are willing to entertain <hi>Truth,</hi> promote <hi>Peace,</hi> and as ready to receive, as to give their Reaſons, I ſay 'tis to ſuch, I addreſs the enſuing <hi>Diſcourſe:</hi> But alas! their Number is but few, and 'tis ſad and deplorable to obſerve, how fierce and zealous the moſt are in maintaining the Side and Party, which <hi>Chance,</hi> Education, Prejudice, Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est or Constitution has engaged them in. And the Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> being ſo pre-ingaged and retained by their reſpective <hi>Parties,</hi> there's few can be prevailed upon to look into the State of the Whole; ſo that amongſt ſo many ſtrugling and contending <hi>Parties,</hi> the <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:52247:4"/>is made good; <hi>Dum ſinguli pugnant univerſi vincun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> Chriſtianity is ruined, and muſt pay all their Reconings. And how ſad and deplorable is the Victory, whoſe Triumph cannot be made, but by the Spoils of Chriſtianity! —<hi>Give thy Son the Heathen for his Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion,</hi> is the Prayer of many of us, and yet at the ſame time, we are ready to pull his Goſpel up by the Roots, if we find it growing any where but in our own little Garden. We have taken an effectual Courſe to prevent our Prayers, and to put a Perfect Stop to its Propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations: For with what Face can we allure or invite any <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then</hi> Nation, or any particular Man, to Eſpouſe our Religion, when we have ſuch Scenes of Miſery and Diſtraction amongſt us, when we can give no Security either to their Souls or Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Amidst our fatal Contests, the one being liable to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, the other to Damnation? But is there no <hi>Balm in Gilead?</hi> No Remedy for theſe things? I have (moved at ſo ſad a Spectacle) amidſt great Avocations, made one poor Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay: But, <hi>Quis tam foelici Sydere natus eſt, ut in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus arduis, in ipſiſſimam ubique veritatem, incidat primo Tentamine,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Jerom;</hi> What Man is ſo happy, amidſt ſo great Difficulties, as to hit the Mark at the firſt Shot? And yet it has had no cold Entertainment, which has encouraged me to venture another Shaft, I here therefore preſent thee with a Second Part, begging no Favour or Approbation, having had it already, from a better hand, <hi>viz.</hi> from our <hi>Saviour</hi> himſelf; who has ſaid <hi>Beati Pacifici,</hi> that the Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>makers are Bleſſed. The Attempt is great for one ſingle <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muncio</hi> to undertake; But the God of Peace and Truth needs neither Strength nor Number to bring his Deſigns to paſs. And whatever the mad World may ſay, or the Iſſue be, it must be ſaid of the <hi>Author,</hi> as of another Great <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaker, <hi>Magnis tamen excidit auſis.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52247:4"/>
            <head>An Expedient for <hi>PEACE</hi> amongſt Chriſtians, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>CHRISTENDOM</hi> makes up a good part of the Habitable World, conſiſting of ſeveral Nations and Kingdoms, Profeſſing but <hi>One Religion,</hi> and that the <hi>beſt</hi> in the World; but the Inhabitants have ſo mixt the Government of this Religion (which purely relates to <hi>Another World</hi>) with the Temporalities and Affairs of <hi>This,</hi> that they are become the Scorn and Deriſion of the more Intelligent parts of Mankind: For whereas they all believe in the Eternal and only True God, and in Jeſus Chriſt his Ever Bleſſed Son: They have ſuch bitter Contentions about <hi>Forms,</hi> and the <hi>True way of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi> about right Interpretation of <hi>Books,</hi> about <hi>Ceremonies, Veſtments, Places, Times</hi> and <hi>Perſons,</hi> their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Offices,</hi> &amp;c. That they make their moſt fruitful Land, an <hi>Aceldama</hi> or <hi>Field of Blood:</hi> Every little Sect, Way and Opinion, is called a <hi>Religion;</hi> and a <hi>Law</hi> is made to <hi>Eſtabliſh it,</hi> and God Almighty entitl'd to the <hi>Truth</hi> of it; and when <hi>He</hi> is concerned, then their Oppoſition can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be too much, but the Powers of the Earth muſt be Pulled down, their Diſſenting Neighbours Deſtroyed, and themſelves undone for the maintaining of it; ſo that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52247:5"/>there is Kingdom againſt Kingdom, and Nation againſt Nation; There is Papiſts and Proteſtants, Calviniſts, Lutherans; Diſſenters, Churchmen, and an endleſs num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of new names of Diſtinction, the curſed motives to miſchief and Diſturbance, as is but too manifeſt at this Day. 'Tis of ſad Conſideration, that Chriſtian Princes muſt have no Allegiance paid them, if of a differing Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion from their Subjects; That when a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Rules, the Pope muſt diſcharge his Subjects from their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; and when a <hi>Popiſh Prince</hi> Reigns, his Proteſtant Subjects diſcharge themſelves — It highly concerns them therefore to think of ſome Remedy and Expedient; for all their Power, their Titles and Crowns, are become Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carious things, and ever and anon ſubject to be laid aſide by the Inſolent Power of the Church, and ill Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Affairs of another World: But time will be ill ſpent in Muſtering up a black liſt of Grievances, when they are ſo Notorious, and ſo much (I will not ſay ſeen but,) felt by all Sides and Parties of Chriſtians of what Quality ſoever, even from the King on his Throne, to the Beggar on the Dunghill; it will be much better ſpent in Contriving of Expedients. And it may juſtly be expected, that any performance of this nature, will rather meet with a favourable acceptance then dicouragement, ſince a thing ſo univerſally wanted by all ſorts of Men.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dove</hi> has been <hi>once ſent out,</hi> but has <hi>return'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain,</hi> finding no place to reſt the Sole of her Foot; The Waters of Confuſion covering the Land: I ſhall preſume to ſend her <hi>once more,</hi> hoping ſhe will find them aſſwaged, and return with an Olive Leaf.</p>
            <p>Then gently laying <hi>Infallibility</hi> aſide, I ſhall reſume my former Argument of Impoſſibility of Agreement, and put it in its place, not only as the more certain and undoubted Truth, but becauſe when a foundation for Peace is laid, it may be expected, it ſhould be a Propoſition univerſally
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52247:5"/>acknowledged and agreed to by all; And this we all know and agree in, <hi>That we can Not Agree:</hi> To this the whole Chriſtian World may ſafely Subſcribe; but if they will not, they cannot convince me to the contrary by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing than their Agreement. Let them Agree then, and I have done. But I ſhall take it for granted, they will not convince me after ſuch a manner, and therefore will go on and ſay, That this Propoſition muſt be one of the chief Stones of the Foundation we muſt Build our Peace upon; we muſt have our Agreement <hi>one</hi> way, from the Impoſſibility of our Agreement <hi>another</hi> way; we muſt have Light out of this thick <hi>Darkneſs;</hi> and order out of <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi> And herein we are inſtructed by the Methods of our all-Wiſe God and Creator, in a caſe of a Paralel Nature.</p>
            <p>For in the Beginning, after he had Created all things out of Nothing, and Spoke things into their Exiſtence, from a formleſs Maſs of Matter, by a wonderful and ſtrange ſort of Chimiſtry; He brought Light out of <hi>Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> and Order out of <hi>Confuſion,</hi> and ſet all things in that moſt exquiſite and incomparable frame and model we ſee them: And all this, not by altering or changing the nature of things differing (for as neceſſary He had Created them ſo) but by bringing things of a like Nature together, or qualifying things of a different Nature, ſo as to make them Agree, and be Harmonious—But for the preſent, waving this Obſervation, it will be neceſſary I Speak ſomething of <hi>Differences</hi> and <hi>Agreements;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the Nature of <hi>This Agreement,</hi> which I ſay is Impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Learned Men have employed their Parts, and been over and above Curious and Critical in vain and unneceſſary Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinctions; in ſuch ſort, that they embroyled the World, and have too much contributed to bring it into the preſent mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and diſtraction: I ſhould be heartily glad now at laſt to ſee them employ their Talents otherwiſe, and as they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52247:6"/>have diſtinguiſhed men into Miſery and Confuſion, ſo now they would try their Skill to diſtiguiſh them out again, and bring the World into Peace and Order: 'Tis but high time they ſhould do ſo, and would they but diſtinguiſh a little and truly inform the world of the Nature of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> and <hi>Diſſention, Diſcord</hi> and <hi>Concord, Agreement</hi> and <hi>Dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference</hi> (for Men have been miſerably miſtaken about theſe things) 'tis my Opinion they would not be ill employed.</p>
            <p>It ought to be obſerved, that amongſt Chriſtians there are ſeveral <hi>ſorts</hi> and <hi>kinds</hi> of <hi>Agreements,</hi> and ſeveral <hi>ſorts</hi> of <hi>Differences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, They Agree in the moſt principal things, and in what they ought to Agree, and this Agreement they call their Difference, though nothing ſo; for they all Agree in their endeavours to pleaſe God; and their various Lines, however differing in the Circumference, do unite in the Center. 'Tis a Maxime, <hi>That things which Agree in a Third, Agree together;</hi> this being well followed, will Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morphoſe moſt of our <hi>Differences</hi> into <hi>Agreements.</hi> Our belief in the Supream God, and his Son Jeſus Chriſt, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and declare an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Agreement:</hi> Now what are all our various ways and Modes of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> but ſo many ſeveral Eſſays and Attempts to pleaſe <hi>This</hi> God, and Teſtifications of our Agreement; and ought rather to be called <hi>parts thereof,</hi> than <hi>Differences:</hi> We all endeavour to <hi>Worſhip God</hi> after the beſt manner we can, and muſt this <hi>way</hi> and this <hi>manner,</hi> and our endeavours herein, be called <hi>Differences?</hi> Indeed the World has branded them along time with that odious appellation, but very improperly, for herein we ſhew nothing more then our Agreement. But to ſpeak the Truth, this is not the Agreement I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for, 'tis indeed a ſort of Agreement we have, and think not of; 'Tis mixt, Partial and Relative, but not productive of Publick Peace. One Man keeps a Feſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val thinking to Pleaſe God thereby, another is afraid and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52247:6"/>ſcrupulous, and will not keep it, thinking to pleaſe him too. Here they both Agree, and both Diſagree. They both agree to Pleaſe God; he that obſerves, and he that obſerves not, obſerves to the Lord, which ought to be a motive of Charity: But then they diſagree and differ one from another, which though they may innocently enough, ye too frequently is made Criminal by exerting their Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to that height, that Charity and their Honeſt Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are conſumed in the Flame.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>They Agree in what they ought not to Agree, viz,</hi> They Conſpire, Cabal and Agree, to Plague, Vex, and Diſturb one another; and this ought not to be called <hi>an Agreement,</hi> but <hi>a Difference:</hi> And of this Nature was the Agreement of <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> and of late but too frequently practiced by <hi>Two Parties</hi> of Chriſtians, in order to ruine the <hi>Third.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, When Men <hi>ceaſe to Moleſt and Disturb one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they are ſaid to Agree;</hi> and when they have made Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulations, and Contracts, we call the Tranſaction an <hi>Agreement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the laſt ſort of Agreement (I principally contend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and in my former Diſcourſe have ſhewed to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible) is that of Men being all of <hi>One Mind, One Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, One Apprehenſion in the matters of Religion,</hi> or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and whenever I ſay <hi>Agreement is impoſſible,</hi> I mean, <hi>this ſort of Agreement,</hi> which really is ſo, and no other.</p>
            <p>Chriſtian Men have indeed taken indefatigable Pains to bring this Agreement to paſs, and cannot as yet be brought to leave off, although oppoſed by God, Nature, and all things Viſible and Inviſible.</p>
            <p>Let us turn our Eyes wherever we Pleaſe, we ſhall ſee nothing but Diverſity and infinite Variety in things; if we look up to Heaven, what ſhall we ſee there, but an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable company of Stars, not ranged and in order, but promiſciouſly placed, <hi>hic et ubique?</hi> Indeed if the Sons of Men had been to have placed them, no doubt but they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52247:7"/>would have put them in Rows and in Order; I mean ſuch a poſition which they call Order: But what they call Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, Unity, and Agreement; The All-Wiſe God eſteems not ſo; He knows and can ſee Beauty; Order, and Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in different Natures and infinite variety of Things, though <hi>They</hi> cannot; and methinks He plainly ſpeaks from Heaven and tells them ſo; having Confronted them with ſuch a glorious appearance of infinitely differing but moſt beautifull <hi>Inſtructors,</hi> which they cannot miſs of ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if they will but look upward: I ſay, one would think they ſhould learn their Leſſon out of this glorious Book of Heaven, wrote in ſuch fair and legible Characters, and ceaſe their vain attemps about an univerſal Order and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. Further, if the Almighty hath not only pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced theſe Heavenly Bodies for Ornament, but alſo hath empowered them to influence the Bodies and Minds of Men (as 'tis poſſible he hath, and many ſuppoſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for) Then this will aggravate their vanity, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring to be more in Order, and more Methodiſed, than their Principals. And they may contend and endeavour to Eternity, but all to no purpoſe; for when they ſhall have Power, or be able to remove the Stars from place to place, or form them into what Figures they pleaſe, diſcharge their Influences, or regulate their Promiſcuouſneſs: Then, and not till then, ſhall they be able to bring their Motly Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to paſs. But as 'tis impoſſible to do the one, ſo not more poſſible to perform the other.</p>
            <p>Then again if we caſt down our Eyes upon Earth, what ſhall we ſee to agree there? 'Tis nothing but a Compoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of things of different qualties and natures, a pregnant Maſs of Matter, productive of infinite Variety of Forms and Shapes. And this is not its Deformity, but Beauty, and it would be but an unpleaſing Heap without it. But after all, we (like Men as we are,) will needs have all to Agree. We would have no Differences, we would have all Men to have One Mind, the Same Opinion, the Same
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52247:7"/>Thought and Apprehenſion of things, and perform Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons after the Same Manner and Method; Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the diſcouragement, and conſtant and ſucceſſive defeats, we have met with in the Proſecution thereof.</p>
            <p>For firſt our Maker defeated <hi>Nimrod</hi> and his Accomplices, the old <hi>Babylonian</hi> Builders, who were contriving and form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to themſelves ſtrange univerſal things, under <hi>One Form, One way,</hi> and <hi>One Government;</hi> as alſo of late, in the Reformation, the <hi>New Babylonian Butlders,</hi> who were carrying on the ſame work, but in an Eccleſiaſtical man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And moſt of the great Invaders of the Earth have met with the ſame misfortune; for ſome of their large Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and Empires, have at this day ſcarce any being but in Records, and that with great difficulty Preſerved. By God Almighties proceeding and dealings with the ſons of Men in the things of this Nature, he ſeems plainly to tell them, That he is not pleaſed with ſuch their univerſal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings. He never yet proſpered or eſtabliſhed univerſal Kings, or univerſal Churches (excepting for ſome little time to puniſh others) but has always pulled down their Build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and reduced them to their primitive Condition and ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion: And whatever eſteem or value they may put upon univerſal Agreements, univerſal Empire or Churches, it doth plainly appear He has not the <hi>ſame.</hi> For he has divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Globe of the Earth by Seas, and Rivers, and Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and allotted each Nation its Limits: And this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion is both Ornamental and Neceſſary, and no Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him at all, for he beholds all the Kingdoms of the Earth, as one Undivided Maſs and Spot of Ground, and all the Generations of Men, as one Stock and Family in one Houſe, but ſeveral Apartments; and though we cry out of Diviſion and Separation, yet he beholds all Chriſtian Aſſemblis <hi>together,</hi> and as in one place, and all to be in the Communion of one Church, as ſo many Figures in one Sum. and all their ſeveral Opinions to be parts of <hi>One</hi> Agreement. So that we need not be ſo fierce to attempt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52247:8"/>impoſſibilities, to fill up the Sea, choak up the Rivers, or level the Mountains, to make all a <hi>Terra Firma;</hi> nor take all that pains which ſome Men do to reconcile Differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and make all men of One Mind, which is equally impoſſible: Which brings me again to my firſt Aſſertion, which ought a little further to be inſiſted on.</p>
            <p>'Tis impoſſible that Chriſtians ſhould Agree in the way and nature they would Agree, not onely for the reaſons men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in my former Diſcourſe, but becauſe there is no common <hi>Standard</hi> fixed and agreed to by all, by which all Parties may take their meaſures, and ſquare and decide their Pretences. Some will have the Pope to be head of the Church, and to be Infallible, and the ſole Judge of all Controverſies and Differences; others will have a General Council; ſome will have both in Conjunction, others neither of them, either apart, or in Conjunction: Some again will have the Scriptures to be Judge, others Tradition; ſome, Scriptures and Tradition together; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers neither Scriptures nor Tradition, but every private Perſon; Some again will have the Church, others the Fathers, ſome neither Church nor Fathers. And what a noiſe have we perpetually ſounding in our Ears about Church, Fathers, Councills, and Scriptures, which are true, and which are ſpurious? The Objections at this time of Day, lie almoſt equally alike againſt all. But if they agree, which are the True, they fall out about the Interpretation, and every Party ſay their own <hi>Comment</hi> is right, and nothing as yet on Earth has been found ſufficient and competent to make a <hi>diciſion.</hi> 'Tis not fit that the <hi>leſs number</hi> ſhould judge for the greater; a <hi>ſingle Man</hi> for a <hi>whole company,</hi> nor a <hi>whole com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany</hi> for a <hi>ſingle Man,</hi> where the matter is Salvation: The Scriptures indeed are the beſt Rule, and the beſt Judge we have, but this onely to private and Particular Perſons for themſelves but not for others, not for publick <hi>Communities;</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52247:8"/>and Societies againſt one another. For the Queſtion, <hi>Who ſhall interpret them,</hi> will never be anſwered; a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Perſon may judge for himſelf, but not for himſelf againſt another; when another is concerned. he is a par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and therefore cannot be Judge: But all the ſeveral Sects and Societies of Chriſtians are Parties, therefore cannot be Judges, neither can Reaſon, Scripture, Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Fathers, Councils, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be Judges, being interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Parties; neither is there a Judge on Earth, but is a Party; Our Agreement therefore muſt be concluded to be impoſſible, and our Differences left to be judged by the God of Heaven, who is only ſufficient and competent for Judgment. From this Impoſſibility therefore of a material Agreement, proved from the infinite variety of humane Underſtandings as men, and from the infinite dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty of things, as Chriſtians, I would lay a Foundation for a formal Agreement, integral and compleat in all its parts, towards God and towards Man; but a further im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provment I ſhall reſerve to the foot of my Diſcourſe, and make Anſwer to a very neceſſary Queſtion which may be asked me, <hi>viz.</hi> Amidſt ſo great Indeterminations and Irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions of men, amidſt ſo many Plauſibilities and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babilities, and infinite Pretentions to Truth, what Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures muſt Men take, or what Rule muſt they walk by? To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p>That's a Reaſon which <hi>convinces,</hi> and that's an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument which <hi>perſwades,</hi> and that's a good Sermon which makes men <hi>better;</hi> beſides thoſe which are the beſt in their kind, and in their own nature really ſo; and he has underſtood Councils, and Fathers, and Scriptures right, who underſtands them in a ſenſe which aſſiſts him to mortifie a Luſt, cruſh an evil Affection, or make him a better Man, although he underſtand them wrong and differing from the original Intent; and 'tis poſſible for a man to underſtand wrong, yet live right; to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52247:9"/>by a ſlender Reaſon, a weak Argument and edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by an ordinary Sermon Every one of theſe, though not the beſt in their kind, yet are equivalent to the beſt, if they produce the Effect of the beſt; And this will put a Check to a great Evil there is in the World, <hi>viz<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> the extravagant Commendation of Preachers Books and Diſcourſes, raiſed often to that height, that Charity is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringed and the Peace endangered. Why muſt the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and moſt ſublime Reaſons be preſſed upon me, when one of a leſſer magnitude doth convince me? And I be forced to hear and may be vilified for not commending ſuch a Brave Preacher, when one of another ſtile and another Method doth more operate upon me and give me better Satisfaction? There is a neceſſity that Truth ſhould be ſerved no and addreſſed to men in various and differing VVays and Methods, becauſe there are Men of various and differing Underſtandings to be wrought upon; and hereby all Books, Comments and Diſcourſes, infinitely differing one from another, according to the differing Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities and Apprehenſions of their Authors, become uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and profitable. And this in a great meaſure may ſerve for anſwer to the Queſtion; but that which muſt make it compleat, is an honeſt Heart and ſincere Endeavours of finding out the Truth, and a ready and willing Diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to comply with it when found: And when men have done their beſt to pleaſe God, and find out the Truth, (as every Party of Chriſtians ſay they do) if they mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, they miſtake <hi>like Men,</hi> and God will never puniſh them for it, for that would be to puniſh them for doing their beſt which ought to be far from the thoughts of every good Chriſtian, ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> they be not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, yet they may be ſafe, ſafe I ſay from the Diſpleaſure and Puniſhment of their Maker thought not of their Fellow-Creatures. For when men have been diligent; honeſt and ſincere, and uſed their utmoſt Endeavours to find
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52247:9"/>out the Truth, pleaſe God, and ſave their Souls, in comes an armed Band of humane Sanctions, Laws, Penalties and Compulſion, to drive them out of this way, which they have judged and pitched upon to be the only true way to Salvation; which brings me to the ſecond Head to be diſcourſed of in order to the Peace of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and that is Law; which I ſhall publickly and ſolemnly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, as the grand Enemy and Diſturber thereof.</p>
            <p>For in the name of the King of Peace, what has Law to do in Religion? Religion ought to be the moſt free, moſt (voluntary and) unconſtrained thing in the World; he that miniſters in it, ought to do it freely and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I and he that performs any Action in it, ought to chooſe it, and be fully convinced and ſatisfied in his Mind; and no Method ought to be uſed either in the Adminiſtration or Propagation, but Argument, Reaſon and Diſcourſe; and it muſt be acknowledged as a moſt certain Truth, That if the whole World joyn together to make a Law, this Law cannot make a Reaſon a good Reaſon, or an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument a good Argument, or make any Propoſition either true or falſe; and if we ask any party of Chriſtians why they uſe ſuch a Method or ſuch a way in Religion? Their Anſwer is, Becauſe they think it true: Since Truth then is and ought to be the Standard and Meaſure by which men ought to determine their Choice, and ſince it is moſt certain, that Law cannot make or determine Truth, Law by a plain and neceſſary conſequence muſt be judged uſeleſs in Religion. Again, If Actions are not voluntary, and Religion be not choſen, there will be no Grounds leſt for either Rewards or Puniſhments, <hi>Nil ardet in Inferno niſi propria voluntas,</hi> nothing burns in Hell but a Man's Will: 'Tis the VVill that makes men criminal, and ſubject to be rewarded or puniſhed; but when there is a Law, there is no Room leſt either to will or to chooſe, but it comes with a <hi>muſt,</hi> with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52247:10"/>and Power, and puts both Religion our Wil and Choice out of doors. And here one may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover the Paw of the <hi>Grand Imposter</hi> and Enemy of Mankind, who when he foreſaw what great Advantages the Religion of the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> would bring to the Sons of Men, by a ſly and crafty Device ſpirited away the <hi>True Babe,</hi> and left us a <hi>Changeling</hi> in his room; he ſtole away <hi>Religion</hi> and left us a <hi>Law,</hi> and ſo effectually brought about his curſed Deſigns and ruin'd us. But further, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Proteſtant Chriſtians Law is the moſt abſurd and vain thing in the world, for they do (and that truly) ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge <hi>the Books of the Old and New Testament</hi> to be the <hi>Only Rule of Faith,</hi> containing full and ample In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions how to <hi>Worſhip God,</hi> and perform all neceſſary Actions in <hi>Religion;</hi> alſo that men in common are able to underſtand, interpret and judge of theſe Books.</p>
            <p>Now if theſe be their Rule and only Rule, what have they to do with <hi>Law,</hi> which is another Rule Our <hi>Saviour</hi> faith, <hi>His Toke is eaſie, his Burden light;</hi> But <hi>Law</hi> is a Tyrant and Uſurper of Chriſtian Priviledges, and lays on heavy Burdens, contrary to the ſweet and gentle Methods of the <hi>Goſpel;</hi> it neither is nor ought to be a Rule to Chriſtians in their <hi>Religion,</hi> and in things relating <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> another VVorld, though it may in their ſecular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns, and in what may relate to this. But ſome will ſay that <hi>Law</hi> is not another Rule, but the ſame, and that it is conſonant to the <hi>Seriptures:</hi> But who muſt be Judge of all this? If one Party uſurp the Power of Judges, 'tis an injury done to all the reſt, and all Proteſtants have been allowed the Priviledge of judging for themſelves, being to be puniſhed themſelves: therefore whatever party uſurps Judgment, makes a <hi>Law,</hi> or affixes a <hi>Penalty,</hi> are to be looked on as Tyrants, and as thoſe who bring in a forreign Power, and invade the Priviledges of their Brethren. But ſuppoſe it agreeable to <hi>Scriptures,</hi> what
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52247:10"/>then? Why then it will be agreeable to Scriptures, and ſo the Point is gained; it will have no Penalty, becauſe Scriptures enjoyn no Penalty, and ſo by conſequence will be no <hi>Law,</hi> but will dwindle away into another thing. and muſt have another name, a Scripture Inference, or a Deolaration what is Truth and agreeable to Scripture, ſuch are all humane Sanctions in relation to <hi>Religion;</hi> Men think they have done ſomething and that they are Parents, and that they have made <hi>Laws,</hi> when alas! they have done nothing, they give their Children Names before they are Born. It muſt be acknowledged in all Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man and Secular Affairs; that in any Kingdom or State Majority of Conſent can make a Sanction which may take the Appellation of a <hi>Law,</hi> and paſs an Obligation of Obedience, and charge a Penalty on the Breach. But in Religion and divine Matters, and things of Eternity, the Scene is changed. Theſe are things <hi>aliend Provinciae &amp; alient Fori,</hi> of another Nature and another Juriſdiction. The Powers of the Earth have nothing to do here, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing neither competent for Cognizance, nor ſufficient to give Judgment in ſuch Matters. Their making Laws and medling in ſuch Mutters as theſe, have ſet the World in a Flame, and when rightly conſidered, it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected it ſhould be otherwiſe. For Temporal things hold no proportion with Eternal, nor the Laws of God with the Laws of Man: That God has given ſome more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and ſpecial Laws to Mankind is moſt certain, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knew the beſt Contrivances, and moſt refined Inventions of Men would be inſufficient, and fall ſhort of reaching all Emergencies: Therefore he has reſerved the Cognizance of ſuch, ſpecial Laws as a particular Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative to himſelf, and that in the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> and not in any humane Judicature. Theſe Laws I mean are the Laws in Mens <hi>Conſciences,</hi> the Laws of <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation,</hi> which neither a greater number for a leſs, nor
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52247:11"/>a leſs for a greater, nor any one Man for another, is to judge of but every ſingle and individual Mann for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and this becauſe every ſingle Man muſt anſwer for himſelf, and be puniſhed for himſelf and not for another. Further, the <hi>Eternal God</hi> has fixed <hi>Eternal Rewards</hi> and <hi>Eternal Puniſhments</hi> to the performance or non perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance of his <hi>Laws:</hi> And it is the higheſt <hi>Reaſon</hi> ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable, that Men ſhould not in the leaſt be honoured, but have all the Freedom which the World is able to afford them in a diſquiſition of ſo great and infinite <hi>Importance,</hi> as the <hi>Salvation</hi> of their <hi>Souls,</hi> and obtaining <hi>Eternal Happineſs,</hi> or ſhunning <hi>Eternal Miſery.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> however plauſibly intereſted Men and the Politicians of the World may diſcourſe for Coercion, their <hi>Reaſons</hi> are vain and fooliſh. For 'tis a moſt certain <hi>Truth,</hi> That no <hi>Chriſtian Prince</hi> can be long ſafe on his <hi>Throne,</hi> nor any <hi>State</hi> long in Peace, where there is any <hi>Let</hi> or <hi>Hindrance</hi> in theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. For what is able to counterballance or ſtand in Competition with <hi>Eternity?</hi> What will not Chriſtian Men, really believing in another World, do to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Eternal Happineſs</hi> or ſhun <hi>Eternal Miſery?</hi> All hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nctions though contrived with never ſo great Art and Subtilty, have hitherto been Baffled, and ſnap'd aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der like <hi>Simplon</hi>'s <hi>Cords,</hi> when theſe <hi>Mighty Philiſtins</hi> have come upon them. When the God of <hi>Heaven</hi> ſpeaks, where ſhall Mortal Man appear? What can humane San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions do when a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Law</hi> appears? When <hi>Eternity</hi> ſpeaks what can <hi>Temporal Puniſhments</hi> prevail? Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to they have not prevailed, and I think I may ſafely af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm they never will.</p>
            <p>Laws in <hi>Religion</hi> therefore muſt be granted me to have no other Tend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cy but to diſturb Men, and to be a moſt effectual <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> keep on foot all the <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances</hi> which Perplex the Chriſtian World. Every Side and Party do really believe, that the Way and Method
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:52247:11"/>they have thoſe to <hi>Worſhip</hi> then Maker, is the Beſt, the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and moſt conducive to make them <hi>Eternally Happy,</hi> and what can be ſuppoſed to be the Conſequence of a Hinderance and a coercive Law to Men ſo thinking, then what we ſee daily practiſed by all of them, <hi>viz. Plotting</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving</hi> the during one another? Can it be ſuppoſed that a Man ſhould be eaſie when he is put out of that way which he really believes the only way that leads to <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Life?</hi> But if it be ſuppoſed he may be eaſie in ſuch a Caſe to yet it cannot be ſuppoſed that he ſhould be caſſe (if he be in his Sences) when he is put into the ready way to <hi>Damnation,</hi> and conſigned to <hi>Eternal Burnings,</hi> which every Side and Party think they are, when by a Law they are forced out of their way? Who then will appear an Advocate for Law in <hi>Religion,</hi> which has ſuch a Natural Propenſity to pull down <hi>Monarchs,</hi> unhinge <hi>Governments,</hi> diſhonour <hi>God</hi> and ruine <hi>Men;</hi> I wiſh I was at a loſs for Inſtances; but alas: they are too ready at hand our own unhappy <hi>Nation</hi> has too long been a Scene of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles on this Account. For whereas we have all done our beſt (as all ſides will ſay) to pleaſe our <hi>Maker,</hi> and every one ſtrove who ſhould come neareſt the Mark: yet ſome has had The good Fortune to be Eſteemed and Rewarded, others to be reproached and puniſhed, and all for doing and endeavouring the ſame things, and all this by a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminating and intervening Law, which can make none of our ways either true or falſe, good or bad. And it muſt be acknowledged that the word <hi>Diſſent</hi> is a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Term, and implies one we diſſent from, and if I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from another, another diſſents from me. So we are both Diſſenters, and Law cannot turn the Scale (being no Judge) ſo that it is a moſt unreaſonable thing, ſince all Arrows are taken out of the ſame Quiver, and equal Probabilities and Plauſibilities brought by all Parties from Scriptures, Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that one ſhould be reſpected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52247:12"/>another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Religion, or rather <hi>Opinion</hi> Eſtabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>Hic pret<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap> ſceleris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> hic D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>: Alexander</hi> for Robbing is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> but another a <hi>Banditti;</hi> one gets a <hi>Crown,</hi> the other a <hi>Gibbet;</hi> one for diſſenting is rewarded, and another for diſſenting is puniſhed, though both have a like Pretention to Truth.</p>
            <p>'Tis Law therefore in <hi>Religion</hi> which I impeach as a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturber of the Peace of <hi>Christendom,</hi> an Occaſion of <hi>Plots,</hi> a Fomenter of <hi>Sedition, Faction</hi> and <hi>Rebellion</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and of moſt of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mongſt us, which being taken away, innum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>able Advantages of Peace would enſue. (But of thoſe in the Concluſion) What for the preſent I ſhall further add, is (with their leave) the <hi>Templers Motto,</hi> with ſome Variation (leaving out the Sword as a ſtrange Inſtrument) and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Let the Truth Live.</l>
               <l>And the Law give</l>
               <l>(<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>)</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>As alſo what the Prophet ſpeaks, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56. and 16. The time being now come ſaith the Lord, <hi>That he who bleſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> himſelf in the God of</hi> Truth; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>by the God of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> are forgotten, and becauſe they are hid from mine E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Which brings me to the third Thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> diſcourſe of in order to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Government, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> enſue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ſaith
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52247:12"/>he by his Prophet <hi>Haggai, It is a little while and I will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth, and the Sea and the dry Land, and I will ſhake all Nations, and the Deſire of all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſhall come, and I will fill this Houſe</hi> (meaning the Temple) <hi>with Glory, ſaith the Lord of Hosts. The Silver is mine, and the Gold is mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts; The Glory of this latter Houſe ſhall be greater than of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts: <hi>And in this Place will I give Peace,</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> Here let me make my Paraphraſe: <hi>By ſhaking the Heavens and the Earth, &amp;c.</hi> is not meant a literal Sence, as ſome would have, nor are the Material Heavens to be ſo ſhaken, but hereby is meant all the Kingdoms, Conſtitutions and Governments of the World; and that the Prophet means ſo, is plain by <hi>verſe</hi> 21 and 22. where he ſaith, <hi>Speak to</hi> Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rubbabel <hi>Governour of</hi> Judah, <hi>ſaying, I will ſhake the Heavens and the Earth, and I will overthrow the Throne of the Kingdoms, and destroy the Strength of the Kingdoms of the Heathen, and I will overthrow the Chariots, &amp;c.</hi> And what is meant by <hi>the Deſire of all Nations?</hi> 'Tis Halcyon days, a peaceable Time, the flouriſhing of the Goſpel, the calling of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and what our Saviour Prayed for, <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come, thy Will be done in Earth as it is in Heaven: The Silver is mine, and the Gold is mine;</hi> that is, I can Adorn and make this Temple as Rich and as Beautiful as I pleaſe: I want nothing which may Embelliſh it, for <hi>the Silver and the Gold is mine, and ſo are the Cattle of a thouſand Hills,</hi> as he told <hi>David;</hi> but 'tis not my De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that ſhould be Adorned with Silver or Gold, and yet the Glory of it ſhall be greater than the former, <hi>for in this Place will I give Peace.</hi> Here by this Temple cannot be meant a Material Temple, either formerly built or to be built, neither of the two Former, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it muſt Exceed them in Glory, and the Glory muſt not conſiſt in a glittering ſhew of Silver or Gold, but of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52247:13"/>Peace: Where let me note, that God doth plainly intimate little Peace has hitherto been in the World, and therefore as a ſpecial Bleſſing doth promiſe, that Peace ſhall be the peculiar Ornament of this Latter Temple; and that we may depend upon his Word and Promiſe, four Times <hi>ſaith the Lord of Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts,</hi> is mentioned in theſe four <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> ſufficient Aſſeverations to Engage the Faith of a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Man. But I cannot leave off my Comment here, but for the Sake and Conſolation of the ſcattered Tribes, ſhall bring the <hi>Prophet</hi>'s Words again to the File. <hi>Yet once, &amp;c.</hi> by which the Living God plainly intimates, That he had often ſhaken the Heavens and the Earth before, that is, the Governments and Kingdoms of the <hi>World,</hi> for the <hi>Material Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth</hi> were ſo far from being ſhaken <hi>often,</hi> that ſince the <hi>Creation,</hi> they <hi>were</hi> never <hi>ſhaken once;</hi> for that of the <hi>Deluge,</hi> was not a ſhaking the Earth or the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, but only a Permiſſion of one Element ſome time to be Predominant, and to return again to its Duty. But not to Expound it by Parts, The Eternal God, the Lord of Hoſts, doth ſeem plainly to ſay thus: <hi>Ye Sons of</hi> Jacob <hi>mine Heri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, my Choſen, Weep not, but be Comforted; though your lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Houſe falls ſhort of the Glory of the former, though you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Adorn it with ſo much Silver and Gold, weep not, I have Silver and Gold enough, I accept your Will and good Endeavours; and know ye, That Heaven is my Throne, and Earth is my Footſtool, What Temple can you make for me? I value not Houſes or Temples, for the Subſtance of theſe things have mine Hand made; but him I value who is Poor, and of a Contrite Spirit, and Trembleth at my Word; but ceaſe your Lamentations and Weeping, though the Glory of the former Temple does far Exceed the Glory of this your latter Temple, yet once, it is a little while, and I will ſhake the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the Earth, and will build you a Temple</hi> (not a Material One) <hi>whoſe Glory ſhall far Exceed the Glory of the former, and in this Place will I give <hi>Peace</hi> ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52247:13"/>
            <p>The Lord of Hoſts is now about to build this Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Temple of Peace, <hi>he is Faithful who hath Promiſed, he is beginning to ſhake the Nations; and to perform his Covenant to his People; Yet a little while and the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſhall bring his Heritage and his Choſen for an Offering to the Lord out of all Nations, upon Horſes, and in Chariots, and in Litters, and upon Mules, and upon ſwift Beasts, to his Holy Mountain at</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>as he has ſpoken by the Mouth of his Prophet; Rejoyce ye therefore with</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and be glad with her, all ye that Love her; Rejoyce for Joy with her, all ye that Mourn for her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here I muſt note that this Promiſe is made to all Nations, but particularly to the <hi>Jews</hi> and to the <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> when to the <hi>Jews,</hi> it is called a Temple; when to <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> a Church: The firſt, long ſince have had their Temple, their High-Prieſt and <hi>Hierarchie,</hi> aboliſhed. The latter; have theirs ſtill in being, which Symbolizes much with the Former, and muſt Symbolize with their Fate, for they muſt now be pulled down.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of CHURCH and STATE.</head>
               <p>HERE is a very great Error, and we form to out ſelves very hurtful and fooliſh Notions of things, we ſuppoſe the Church and State to be <hi>Two</hi> Things, and in all our Diſcourſes name them at <hi>Twice,</hi> whereas they <hi>really</hi> are but <hi>One:</hi> for the Church <hi>is in</hi> the State, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>is</hi> the State; for when the Nations of the World at firſt became <hi>Christian,</hi> and receiv'd the Faith of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> they became <hi>better</hi> Nations, and the Inhabitants <hi>better</hi> People, having receiv'd <hi>better</hi> Maxims and Principles, but ſtill the <hi>ſame</hi> People; and they ſtood in <hi>Statu quo,</hi> as to all Power or Adminiſtration of their Affairs. The Religion which
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52247:14"/>came amongſt them, made no alteration of Things, but for the <hi>better,</hi> gently infuſing it ſelf with as little noiſe as Rain on a Fleece of Wool: its Miniſtry was of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and not of <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Dominion;</hi> it claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Power, being it wanted none; its whole Deſign and Drift relating to things of another World, or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to promote <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs</hi> in this; and happy had it been for <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> had its Nations and States on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been called <hi>Christian,</hi> and its Princes looked on this Religion only as good Qualities in their Subjects, tending to promote <hi>Obedience</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> in their Kingdoms, and gave it an Eſtabliſhment on this Account: And the ſo much celebrated Name of <hi>Church,</hi> had never been heard of in the Nature it has been uſed. Alſo when they ſent Judges to miniſter Juſtice to their Subjects, had they with them ſent Miniſters to Preach the Goſpel, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it in ſuch a ſort of way to this Time, I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded the Author would never had occaſion to write Expedients for Peace at this day. But here lay their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, ſeeing its Miniſtry was of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Godlineſs,</hi> and not of <hi>Empire</hi> and <hi>Dominion,</hi> they looked on the thing <hi>in</hi> them, as divided <hi>from</hi> them; and would needs give it a <hi>new</hi> Name, and inveſt it with <hi>Power,</hi> which though little at firſt, by degrees rival'd their <hi>own,</hi> and ſince has joſtled many of them out of their Thrones: And now they have Leaſure to Repent themſelves of their bad Logick, in dividing the Accidents from their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects and ſetting up Non entities. For the Church is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all, a mere Metaphyſical Term; and when <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Princes</hi> Govern their <hi>People</hi> well, they Govern the <hi>Church</hi> well: for the Church is in the People, or rather the People are the Church. But if they ſet up a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment or a Government in their Kingdoms diſtinct from their own, they do but Nurſe a <hi>Viper</hi> in their own Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoms, and they cannot in Reaſon expect their Crowns
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52247:14"/>ſhould ever ſit eaſie on their Heads amidſt the unavoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Emulation of two diſtinct Governments. The Church and State are a <hi>Chriſtian State,</hi> and but <hi>one,</hi> and ſo at firſt appointed by the God of Heaven, and what God hath joyned, no man ought to put aſunder. And I humbly conceive, that Men profeſſing Chriſtianity, ought to have no diſtinct Government from the State, I am ſure they were much better Chriſtians when they had none. The Apoſtles propagated the Faith of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the <hi>Gentile</hi> World, and the <hi>Eccleſiae,</hi> or <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greated to perform Acts of Devotion in the way which they had Taught, are called Churches; and when we read of the Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> or of this or that Church, nothing elſe is to be underſtood but the Congregation of <hi>Believers</hi> met to pay <hi>Homage</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> to their Maker in the Name of <hi>Jeſus;</hi> which was done in a plain and ſimple Manner, never enterfering with, or diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Government of the Place. Neither Power, nor Policy or Skill, can be needful for a few honeſt and inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Men, to meet together in a peaceable manner to Worſhip God, all the Requiſites in ſuch a Caſe, are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>Sincere Heart,</hi> and a <hi>Willing Mind:</hi> What need we then ſo much Eccleſiaſtical Policy and Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment? Or if we muſt have it, why muſt ſuch <hi>Frames</hi> and <hi>Machines</hi> be called the Church? This is to call the Scaffold, the Building. But after all, 'tis moſt certain, that only <hi>True Believers</hi> and <hi>good Livers</hi> are the Stones which make up that Heavenly Building, and are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly True Church of Chriſt, againſt which the Gates of Hell ſhall be never able to prevail.</p>
               <p>But we talk of ſetting <hi>up</hi> or pulling <hi>down</hi> Churches, in as material a Sence, as when we Erect or pull down Houſes; and one laments the pulling down ſuch a rare Eſtabliſhed Church, and mightily oppoſes the Building of another, and we all think our <hi>own Cottages, Pallaces;</hi>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52247:15"/>and are always commending our <hi>own Church,</hi> and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commending anothers; and ſuch a ſtir we make about our <hi>Churches,</hi> that makes us <hi>Ridiculous</hi> to all the World; and no wonder <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> has been ſo long Embroiled, ſince we have had ſo many <hi>Churches,</hi> that is, ſo many Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and Cauſes of <hi>Diſturbance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There is but <hi>One</hi> God, <hi>one</hi> Chriſt, <hi>one</hi> Faith, <hi>one</hi> Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>one</hi> Religion, and but <hi>one</hi> Church; and the ſeveral Perſwaſions, make but one <hi>Religion;</hi> and ſeveral ways of <hi>Worſhip</hi> and diſtinct <hi>Congregations</hi> but <hi>one</hi> Church: But we call the Parts the whole, and a ſingle Houſe a Town, and are in a continual Alarm in Defence of our little Reſpective Cittadels. And to that height of Abuſe is the Name of Church now Grown; that to be of This or That Church, is to compound for a good Life; and Men think if they belong to <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> a Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, all will go well with them; and having ſo many Parties amongſt us, and ſo many Intereſts to be ſerved, the neceſſity of proſelyting Men to their ſide, rather than to <hi>Goodneſs</hi> or <hi>Truth,</hi> doth but too much contribute to it; and <hi>ſome Guides</hi> are but too willing to indulge Men in their Vice, ſo they will but be of <hi>their</hi> Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: But hower we may value our ſelves, one for being of <hi>this</hi> Church, and another for being of <hi>that;</hi> I am afraid if we live not good Lives, we ſhall be found at laſt to be of <hi>no</hi> Church at all. Our Saviour tells us, <hi>he that doth Righteouſneſs, is Righteous; and that the Tree is known by its Fruit;</hi> if we Live well, we ſhall be of God's Church, and if we Live ill, we ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly be <hi>out</hi> of the Church: however we may be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Men with the greateſt <hi>Solemnity</hi> and <hi>Ceremony</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that Society we call by that Name. <hi>Templum Domini, Templum Domini,</hi> was the Cry of the <hi>Jews,</hi> and now is the Cry of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and ſufficiently abuſed by both. We all know the Fate of theirs, and the Reaſons;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52247:15"/>and in knowing this, we may eaſily Calculate the Fate of our own: For their <hi>Temple</hi> and our <hi>Church</hi> exactly anſwer one another, I mean our <hi>Political Hierarchical Church;</hi> The Conſtitution of which, is fixed in a Diametri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Oppoſition to <hi>Publick Peace,</hi> and we can never expect Peace to flouriſh in <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> ſo long as one Stone of this ill-built Fabrick doth lie upon another. Then in order to the Pulling down this <hi>Myſtical Babel,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I here moſt ſolemnly declare and proteſt againſt all the <hi>Preſent Constitutions</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Corporations</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> as injurious to <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Tranquili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and very much diſſerving all <hi>Temporal Government,</hi> thwarting and croſſing the juſt Deſigns of <hi>Princes,</hi> and on all Occaſions miniſtring to <hi>Faction, Sedition</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion,</hi> and againſt all differing <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions</hi> of Chriſtians whatſoever, which are any way endowed with <hi>Immunities, Priviledges,</hi> or any Temporal <hi>Power, Preferment</hi> or <hi>Benefices,</hi> independant of the State. And ſince all the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>States</hi> of <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> are in a Fermentation and Motion, 'tis my Opinion, that if they would (after an Act Paſſed for the Relief of the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Incumbents) ſeize all <hi>Temporal Endowments</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices</hi> appropriated to <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Churches,</hi> and diſſolve and make Null all <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Decrees, Canons, Charters</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions,</hi> They would do the greateſt Service to <hi>Chriſtianity, Publick Peace,</hi> and Themſelves, as ever has happened to the World, ſince the firſt Propagation of ſo Holy a Religion. <hi>Ouc agathon polycoironie, &amp;c.</hi> ſaith the old Poet; which with deference, I interpret, One <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and one <hi>Power</hi> in a Nation, is enough. But if <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Government</hi> muſt go down, ſome like <hi>Saul,</hi> will be for ſaving <hi>Amaleck</hi> and the beſt of the Cattle, their Wealth and Riches: To which I anſwer, theſe muſt not be ſaved, for <hi>Dominion</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> are inſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to Wealth and Riches; therefore theſe muſt be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52247:16"/>before <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Wrath can be appeaſed, or Peace be ſettled in our Iſrael.</hi> But in Anſwer, methinks I hear a great noiſe of <hi>Profaneneſs, Sacriledge,</hi> and the <hi>Ruine</hi> of of all Religion, but I ſhall be deaf to the Objection, ſince in plain truth, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> of it is no more <hi>Then Great is</hi> Diana <hi>of the</hi> Epheſians. For Religion would not at all be in hazard or concerned in ſo great a Change, but would be purified and cleanſed, and appear much more amiable and Eligible, it would but diveſt her of her ſordid Rags, knock off her Fetters, and leading her out of the Squalid Priſon of <hi>Terrene</hi> and Temporal Mixtures, cloath her with <hi>Royal Robes,</hi> and reſtore her to her <hi>Throne</hi> and <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Religion of the <hi>Holy Jeſus</hi> is (God be thanked, at this time of the Day) ſo well propagated, that there is no danger of its being loſt, if <hi>Honours,</hi> and <hi>Preferments,</hi> and all Secular <hi>Advantages</hi> be diſcharged her <hi>Retinue,</hi> and ſecluded her Family: For they make no Conſtituent or Eſſential Parts of her, but are things which her miſtaken but well-meaning Votaries have given her, to Adorn and Bedeck her, but really have diſguiſed and deformed her. For her <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Empire</hi> is <hi>over,</hi> nay <hi>in</hi> the <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Conſciences</hi> of Men; teaching them to live good Lives, and to follow the Example and Precepts of the moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Author, whoſe Life and Doctrine was a of ſpiritual Nature, abſtracted and ſeparate from all Vain Glory, Pomp and Splendor, who did utterly Renounce the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of Inheritances, and publickly declare his Kingdom was not of this World.</p>
               <p>His <hi>Religion</hi> therefore miniſtring in the Affairs of his <hi>own</hi> Kingdom, <hi>viz.</hi> of Heaven, Grace and Glory, ought to be kept ſeparate and pure, and not mixt with the Things and Powers of this World. The Engliſh of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le per Ann.</hi> is not taking up the Croſs, nor does Grace and Godlineſs eccho right to Honours and Revenues. Faith,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:52247:16"/>Hope and Charity are <hi>Fundamentum, Paries &amp; Tectum;</hi> The <hi>Foundation, Walls</hi> and <hi>Roof</hi> of Chriſt's <hi>True Church</hi> upon Earth; other Structures which we call Churches, are nothing at all, and if we can procure Means, or get Builders to rear this <hi>Heavenly Fabrick,</hi> implant theſe <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Qualifications</hi> in the Hearts of Men, our Work is done. The old <hi>Building</hi> muſt come down, and the old <hi>Builders</hi> muſt be rejected, who have built with untem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered <hi>Mortar;</hi> have mixt Temporals with Spirituals; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>Humility</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> have put Pride and Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and in the room of <hi>Mortification</hi> and <hi>Self-denyal,</hi> have placed Wealth and Honours, and have fenced all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout with a <hi>High Wall</hi> of an uſurped Power and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Other <hi>Meaſures</hi> therefore muſt be taken, and a new <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> exhibited, ſince moſt of what hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to have been taken, muſt be acknowledged to be <hi>miſtaken,</hi> and not calculated for publick Peace.</p>
               <p>Chriſt has been <hi>Preached</hi> indeed, Grace <hi>Adminiſtred,</hi> and Souls <hi>Saved;</hi> but the <hi>Manner</hi> and <hi>Method</hi> of Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration has been <hi>irregular</hi> and <hi>unhappy,</hi> Miniſtring rather Matter of <hi>Diſturbance,</hi> than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny Advantages to the <hi>Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs</hi> of <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Governme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> of the World. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unhappy <hi>Monarchs</hi> diſturbed in their Meaſures of <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> by ſtrugling Parties, and contending Churches, abuſed by <hi>Ambitious</hi> and <hi>Diſcontented Biſhops;</hi> eſpecially by him who is ſo notorious, and has ſo often Signalized himſelf by Affronting <hi>Crowned Heads,</hi> and perplexing their <hi>Affairs,</hi> are ſad Inſtances, and but too eaſily Verifie the Charge.</p>
               <p>And for the ſeveral Forms and Ways of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> and <hi>Administration,</hi> however all Parties and Sects of <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> pretend they find them in the <hi>Scriptures;</hi> They are no more able to find them there, than they are able to find the ſeveral Figures of <hi>Birds, Beasts</hi> and <hi>Fiſhes</hi> in the <hi>Heavens,</hi> which the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> tell us are there. They may find <hi>faint Reſemblances</hi> indeed, but no <hi>Plain</hi> and ſelf-evident
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52247:17"/>
                  <hi>Schemes:</hi> The Reaſon is, becauſe none is of <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute</hi> Neceſſity to <hi>Salvation,</hi> and we muſt entertain very mean and low Thoughts of the <hi>Goodneſs</hi> of the: All-wiſe Being, to let poor Mortals ramble in the <hi>Dark</hi> for ſo many <hi>Ages,</hi> and ſubject them to an <hi>Eternal Search</hi> and wrangling about Schemes and Forms of <hi>Government</hi> of his Church. If <hi>any at all</hi> had been abſolutely neceſſary, his <hi>Bleſſed Son,</hi> who came to Reveal all his Will, would have fixed it as plain as the Sun in the <hi>Firmament,</hi> that it ſhould not be in our Power to miſtake: And if no <hi>Church-Government</hi> at all be neceſſary, then it follows of Courſe, that no particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Way</hi> or <hi>Model</hi> is neceſſary; and indeed if we conſider things narrowly, a Coat may as well be made for the <hi>Moon,</hi> as any particular Way be preſcribed. The Flux and Reflux, and infinite uncertainty of humane Affairs, will not admit of it; as long and as often as <hi>Men ſin,</hi> they muſt be <hi>Puniſhed,</hi> but this cannot be done, unleſs there be <hi>Disturbances,</hi> and ſetting up and pulling down <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, Nations</hi> and <hi>Families;</hi> and ſince it is neceſſary there ſhould be ſo great <hi>Changes,</hi> what particular Scheme can be drawn to fit all <hi>Circumſtances?</hi> But ſome will ſend me to the <hi>Apostles</hi> and to the <hi>Primitive Times:</hi> But to this I anſwer, That what they might then preſcribe, ought not to be drawn down for a <hi>Preſident</hi> to theſe Times. The Church then was under <hi>Heathens</hi> and <hi>Perſecutors,</hi> and but in its Infancy, and if we take their <hi>Meaſures,</hi> we put a Childs Coat on a Man's Back, which is but an ill ſight; but yet it is done by us, and is a Folly we are ſo fond of, that neither the <hi>Inconveniences</hi> we labour under, nor the <hi>juſt Deriſion</hi> we incur thereby, can make us forego. We find indeed in the Scriptures, <hi>Epiſcopi, Presbiteri, Diaconi,</hi> but not exhibited to us in ſuch commanding and indiſpenſible <hi>Terms,</hi> as to paſs an <hi>Obligation</hi> and <hi>Neceſſity</hi> on all <hi>Ages</hi> of the Church, and all <hi>Mankind,</hi> to have the <hi>ſame.</hi> But if <hi>Men</hi> uſeful, ſerving the <hi>Same Purpoſes</hi> and <hi>Ends,</hi> and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52247:17"/>more Conducive to Publick <hi>Tranquillity</hi> in theſe latter <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of the World, after ſo great a <hi>Change</hi> of <hi>Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> and <hi>Corruption</hi> of <hi>Manners,</hi> by the Supream Power of any <hi>Nation</hi> ſhall be thought fit to be choſen, no matter whether they have the <hi>ſame Names</hi> or no, or any <hi>Names</hi> at all, ſo they ſerve the <hi>ſame Ends;</hi> for the <hi>Buſineſs</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is not a thing of <hi>Names</hi> and <hi>Titles,</hi> but a <hi>Subſtantial</hi> Thing, productive of Holineſs, Piety, and Charity: And whatſoever <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> which may be thought <hi>Fit</hi> and <hi>Convenient</hi> to promote her <hi>Intereſt,</hi> and <hi>Miniſter</hi> to her Neceſſity, may without Scruple be adopted into her <hi>Family.</hi> And all <hi>Preſent Methods</hi> of <hi>Government</hi> and <hi>Ways</hi> of Adminiſtration, if found diſſerving the <hi>Ends</hi> of Publick <hi>Peace</hi> and True <hi>Religion,</hi> may be innocently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, and new ones <hi>Choſen,</hi> according to the <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Diſcretion</hi> of the <hi>Supream Power.</hi> And the Reaſon is, becauſe all <hi>Offices</hi> and <hi>Functions</hi> Eccleſiaſtical, and <hi>all</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods and Ways of <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> in the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Holy Jeſus,</hi> make no parts of it, but are <hi>Extrinſecal</hi> to the Nature of the thing, therefore may be changed or alter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the forementioned Account.</p>
               <p>The greateſt <hi>Oppoſition</hi> to <hi>this</hi> will be made by thoſe who pretend to their <hi>Functions</hi> by a <hi>Commiſſion</hi> from Heaven, and by a <hi>Divine Right;</hi> but theſe are of two ſorts. The firſt I believe will quickly lay down their <hi>Pretenſions,</hi> when the <hi>Grandeur</hi> of the Church is <hi>Diminiſhed,</hi> and her <hi>Power,</hi> her <hi>Law,</hi> and <hi>Riches,</hi> are taken away; The latter, who may be innocently Abuſed, and think themſelves under an indiſpenſable <hi>Obligation</hi> of Preaching the Goſpel, muſt be let alone, there is no Remedy for them but <hi>Time,</hi> which 'tis poſſible by degrees may let them ſee their Error, and leſſen their <hi>High Thoughts</hi> of their Fitneſs, and ſufficiency of undertaking ſo great a <hi>Charge.</hi> But however it may happen, the <hi>Predication</hi> of no <hi>Pretenders</hi> can affect the Publick Peace, when both <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> to do hurt, are taken from them, and the Matter and Subject of their
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52247:18"/>Diſcourſes are purely <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> and relating to the things of <hi>another World.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But by way of Recapitulation, &amp; in order to a Concluſion. The Foundations to be laid for a <hi>New Settlement,</hi> are, Firſt,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Impoſſibility of Agreement, and Innocency of Differences.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, <hi>That the Church be converted into a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an State, that ſhe needs no Law, no Power, or Revenues.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, <hi>That whatever Forms or Ways of Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Religion, or the Church, hath hitherto been uſed, may innocently and lawfully be changed.</hi> Then the Plain and neceſſary Conſequences will be theſe:</p>
               <p>When <hi>Agreement</hi> is <hi>Impoſſible,</hi> Men will <hi>ceaſe</hi> to attempt it; and when <hi>Differences</hi> are made <hi>Innocent,</hi> the infinite variety of Underſtandings and Apprehenſions of Men will be no more hurtful or offenſive, then their different Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: When there is <hi>no Government,</hi> all Contentions which is the <hi>right,</hi> will ceaſe; and where there is <hi>no</hi> Law, there will be <hi>no</hi> Tranſgreſſion, and by conſequence <hi>no</hi> Delinquents to be puniſhed; and when there is <hi>no</hi> Power, there will be <hi>no</hi> danger of abuſing it; And how ſoon ſhall we ſee the the flames of Contention <hi>ceaſe,</hi> when the combuſtible Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el of Wealth, and Power, and Honours, are taken away? But further, At the very ſound of impoſſibility of Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a ceſſation of <hi>all</hi> Controverſies muſt neceſſarily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue, and this Doctrine doth preſently ſummon all the moſt skilful and learned in the Art of Wrangling, to lay down their Arms and live Peaceably; and how happy muſt the Chriſtian World be, when rid of ſuch Seditious Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, that ſo long have diſturbed her Peace? Then the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>no Government,</hi> is not leſs Advantageous and Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial; for at one breath it tumbles down all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Hierarchies, and gives eaſe to the <hi>groaning</hi> and <hi>miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Potentates</hi> of the Earth; it anſwers all the Prayers of the Saints for many Ages; and like a voice from Heaven, or the Trump of God, Tumbles down the mighty Man of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52247:18"/>Sin, or Whore of <hi>Babylon,</hi> from her Throne: And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks I ſee the Princes of the Earth already in Council againſt her, to pull down her Pride, and diveſt her of her Power, which ſo long has been uſed againſt them: Then for <hi>Law,</hi> that being baniſhed, Chriſtian Men would then begin to look Innocently, and the great Machine of Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution and Rapine would fall to the Ground; Wicked Men would have no pretence to exerciſe their Cruelties, and the Earth would no more Groan and Cry out for Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for the Blood of Saints, Martyrs, and Profeſſors, that has been ſpilled upon her: 'Tis theſe Laws that are the ſharp Teeth with which Chriſtians devour one another; they might Diſpute and Argue with Innocence and Safety, were but theſe Weapons lay'd out of their way, which they too often ſnatcht to compleat the Victory, and to the ruine of each other.</p>
               <p>But by this time men will ſay my deſign tends to unhinge all Governments, to deſtroy all Laws, and to make no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>Confuſion</hi> in the World: To this I anſwer, That there was Darkneſs before Light, Confuſion before Order, and whoever will have a new Houſe, muſt have ſome trouble in the building, and endure the Inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of puling down the old One: But this is not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, but in further anſwer to the Objection, I deſire to have it obſerved, That the Chriſtian World <hi>is</hi> in <hi>Confuſion already,</hi> that I <hi>make</hi> no diſturbance, but <hi>find</hi> it; that I cannot Confound them more then they are already Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded; that Governments are unhinged, and Laws broke, and Princes in Arms, ready to deſtroy one another, and one of the principal occaſions is <hi>Religion;</hi> therefore ſome great thing is the matter; 'Tis either in the Religion itſelf, or in the Managery and Adminiſtration of it; the firſt I acquit; the latter I lay my Accuſation againſt, and charge the Adminiſtrators with aſſuming <hi>Power</hi> and making <hi>Laws,</hi> and Erecting a <hi>Mock Government,</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:52247:19"/>which has Ruined and Confounded the State, and all <hi>True</hi> Laws and <hi>True</hi> Governments: I therefore ſhall take the Liberty to move and ſuggeſt ſome Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations for a New and Better way of Adminiſtration; and I hope my undertaking will find a Favourable Acceptance amongſt all good Men.</p>
               <p>Then the Adminiſtration of the Religion of the Holy <hi>Jeſus,</hi> may be divided into two parts, <hi>Ordinary</hi> and <hi>Extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary;</hi> the <hi>Ordinary,</hi> which conſiſts of Prayers and Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and Diſpenſations of Charity, to be Perform'd by <hi>ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary</hi> Men; I hope it will not be deny'd me, but that Men in Common are capable of performing ſuch things, after ſome few Leſſons taught them of the nature and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes of the Being they are to Petition and Adore; other Requiſites are only a <hi>Sence</hi> of their Wants, and Mercies received, which almoſt naturally will make them both <hi>Eloquent</hi> and <hi>Grateful.</hi> As to their meeting together, this will require no great Art or Subtilty, nor will the <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place</hi> meet with greater Difficulty: <hi>Wherever Two or Three are gathered together in my Name,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, <hi>I will be in the midſt of them;</hi> there is neither Time and Place mentioned, nor the Quality or Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities of the Perſons to meet, but all runs in an indefinite Manner. By <hi>two or three,</hi> either may be meant ſo many, in a literal Sence, or a certain Number for an uncertain, but however a <hi>poſse</hi> to congregate, or gather together, muſt neceſſarily be implyed and allowed to Men in common, from this indefinite Text. And notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding all the great noiſe of Diſagreement, Diſſenters and Schiſmaticks, if Men can <hi>agree</hi> ſo to meet together to pay Homage to the great God in the Name of Jeſus, their Agreement is ſufficient, and here is a Bleſſing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed them from this plain Text, which I hope will be ſufficient to diſcharge me from the Reproach of an Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator. As for their <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Way, &amp;c.</hi> God muſt be Judge
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52247:19"/>of it, and not Men. Let there therefore be given to Men a Power to Congregate, and in their Reſpective Congregations, let them chooſe what Men they think fit to diſpence their Charity, and to be Judges of the Lives of their Fellows, ſo as to Expell them their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations if Occaſion require. Let them call theſe men by <hi>what Names</hi> they pleaſe. But let there be <hi>no Laws</hi> amongſt them, but thoſe of <hi>Reverence</hi> and <hi>Reſpect,</hi> of <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Fear,</hi> which are <hi>the beſt and only Laws</hi> which Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians ought to have in their <hi>Oeconomy.</hi> But if they break theſe gentle Bonds, Then <hi>Currat Lex,</hi> let the Secular Power take Place. This for the <hi>ordinary part</hi> of the Adminiſtration to be performed by <hi>ordinary</hi> men, or men <hi>in Common.</hi> As for the <hi>Extraordinary,</hi> which is the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments,</hi> to be performed by Men ſeparated, and of better Capacities, let it be thus:</p>
               <p>When the Supream Power of each <hi>Chriſtian Nation,</hi> have ſet themſelves <hi>in Statu quo,</hi> diſſolved all Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Governments, and reſumed from the Church her uſurped and deſtructive Power and Revenues, (the firſt muſt be never given her again, the laſt put to better U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes.) <q rend="margQuotes">Then I ſay let them build and Erect in the midſt of each Reſpective Nation, <hi>Magnum Collegium Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> a large Chriſtian Colledge, and Endow it with ſuch Priviledges and Conveniences, as may be thought fit and Proper, <hi>&amp;c. Then let the Wiſdom of each Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> (after having asked their Willingneſs) <hi>chooſe a conſiderable number of Youth, of the hopefullest Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Body and Mind; and after publick Addreſſes made to the Living God, by Fasting and Prayer, for an auſpicious Election, let Lots be Caſt, and on whom the Lots do fall, let them receive an Order from the State, to Enter into the ſaid Colledge, to Fit and Qualifie themſelves to be Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and Ministers of the Goſpel; and after ſuch a Term
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52247:20"/>of years continuance, as ſhall be thought fit, let a certain number be brought forth; and the question of Willingneſs being asked, and Addreſſes made to Heaven, as afore-ſaid, let Lots proportioned to the National Wants be caſt, and on whom the Lots do fall, let a convenient and honourable Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance be ſetled, and let them receive their Commiſſion from the State, to Preach the Kingdom of Heaven, and Jeſus Chriſt Crucified, and Minister the Word and Sacraments in a plain, decent, and orderly manner, as near as poſſible they can to the firſt Institution: And when the Judges ſet out in the King or States Name, to distribute Juſtice, and determine Law, let them alſo</hi> per Order <hi>of the King or State, Preach the Kingdom of Heaven and the Goſpel, in the ſame Itinerant and Circular manner, through all the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Towns of each Reſpective Kingdom, inſtructing the People in the moſt pure Doctrine and Belief of the Holy Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and in all the moſt Neceſſary and Fundamental Points of his Religion (a definition of which, 'tis poſſible,</hi> Volente Deo, <hi>may be the Subject of another Diſcourſe</hi>) <hi>and let their Subjects be levelled againſt Sedition and Rebellion, Exhibit Peace in its beſt Apparel, Extoll Juſtice, Mercy and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and whatever may tend to the Glory of God, or Peace and Well-fare of Man-kind, and not at all to meddle with Law, the State, or Government; always remembring they are not appointed Miniſters of State, but of the Goſpel. And if a diſtinct performance was allotted for ſuch and ſuch a Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit, it would not do amiſs,</hi> viz. <hi>Inſtructing and Proſelyting for one, Baptizing for another, and giving the Sacrament for a Third, or varying theſe, as may be thought moſt fit and convenient, doubling the firſt, or intermitting the laſt: Or if from the ſaid Colledge, having Twelve Gates, they ſhould go out every Month and Heal the Nations (which Scripture indigitates) nothing can be thought of more convenient.</hi>
                  </q> This way and method, I hope, will eaſily be allowed me to be ſufficient for the Salvation of Souls; and would but
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:52247:20"/>the Princes and States of Chriſtendom conſent to ſettle ſuch an <hi>oeconomy,</hi> the plain Conſequences thereof would be,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Popery,</hi> that <hi>wicked thing,</hi> ſo much hated and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by <hi>Protestants,</hi> not only for its own innate Evils, but alſo its Collateral and Accidental ones; being the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Tool which all Parties uſe to ſet up, or pull down one another, would in a moment be buried in Oblivion; and <hi>Hereſy,</hi> its Twin and Brother in Iniquity, would be bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in the ſame Grave. A new Heaven and a new Earth would ſuddenly appear; all the Diſturbing Names of <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> and <hi>Proteſtants, Schiſmatick</hi> and <hi>Heretick,</hi> would ſpeedily ceaſe; we ſhould have no Sides nor Parties of Chriſtians; no bitter Contentions which is the <hi>True Church;</hi> the Indefatigable Pains of compaſſing Sea and Land to make <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> would be at an end, and all the miſchievous Conſequences attending thereon: Now all Sides and Parties are Induſtrious to make Converts, and give their Reaſons and Arguments, and yet at the ſame time Interpretatively would not have them taken, for none meets with greater Shame and Ignominy then Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts, who if they obey their own, or are convinced by others Reaſons, are ſaid to <hi>change</hi> their Religion (as they call it) and are hated and abhorred; ſo that men in a great meaſure, are under an obligation to ſtick to their Principles, whether they be <hi>good</hi> or <hi>bad,</hi> becauſe of the Reproach they of neceſſity muſt meet with if they <hi>change</hi> them. And alas! Theſe which they call their Principles and Religion, are nothing but ſome fond and unneceſſary Opinion, which <hi>may be changed</hi> and no <hi>hurt</hi> at all done. But <hi>then</hi> men would have no Temptation to change, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>no</hi> Party to go to, <hi>no</hi> Sect to maintain, and <hi>no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church</hi> to defend; which are the common Themes of Chriſtian men, and at this time make but too great Part of their Religion, and too frequently mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters matter of their Mutual Ruine. Again, Now moſt of our time is ſpent in commending our ſelves and <hi>our</hi>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:52247:21"/>way, and diſcommending others, &amp; their way; and Three parts of our Religion, is made up of nothing but Vapour and Smoke, of mere Talk and finding of Faults; if we can <hi>charge</hi> and <hi>accuſe,</hi> and make <hi>others</hi> Guilty, and <hi>our ſelves</hi> Innocent, 'tis <hi>Religion</hi> enough: And amongſt ſo many contending Parties of <hi>Christians,</hi> 'tis almoſt <hi>impoſſible</hi> any Juſtice ſhould be done, the Spirit of <hi>Partiality</hi> ſo reigneth amongſt us: But <hi>Terras Astraea Reviſit.</hi> Then Juſtice would run down our Streets like a mighty Stream, and all the Parts, the Piety, and Learning, at leaſt wiſe Honeſty, which is certainly amongſt moſt Parties of Chriſtians, would have their due Effects, and appear in their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Colours, when cleared from the <hi>Foggs</hi> and <hi>Miſts</hi> of <hi>Contentious Diſputes,</hi> which confines them to their proper Orbs, and will not ſuffer them to be Communicative, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe their Rayes, but give a dim and partial Light. <q rend="margQuotes">Fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Now no Oath can bind, no Benefits oblige, no Prince Reign, but all the moſt Sacred Bonds of Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, Honour and Obedience, and every other thing which may make men wiſh to Live, are violated and broken aſunder, if Religion, or that which men call by that Name, ſtand in Competition, or Mother-Church is to be ſerved; and men pull down Houſes, tumble down Monarchs, and ruine Kingdoms for her ſake. Sure then thoſe muſt be happy days, when no particular <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Church</hi> is to be ſet up, nor any to be pull'd down, no Party to be pleaſed, and none to be offended, but every Nation will be all of one Side, one Party, and the ſame Religion: And of how great Refreſhment and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is it, to think that that hot and fiery Zeal which has burnt ſo many Martyrs, and conſumed ſo many Pious and Good men, nay, deſtroyed the Lord of Life himſelf, ſhall be abſolutely and for ever quenched in the Springs of this moſt <hi>Charitable</hi> and <hi>Refreſhing</hi> Fountain, which from the Heart of each <hi>Reſpective Kingdom</hi> ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly running, and refreſhing the dry and barren Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:52247:21"/>of the ſame; and like ſo many Rivulets of Oyl, ſhall paſs through the great Ocean of the World, and Heal, and Cleanſe, and Purify, but not mix with the ſame: But what ſhould I ſay?</q>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ltima Cumaei Venit jam carminis aetas,</l>
                  <l>Magnus ab integro Seclorum naſcitur ordo;</l>
                  <l>Jam redit &amp; Virgo, redeunt Saturnia Regna.</l>
               </q>
               <p>The Happineſs which this Adminiſtration will moſt certainly bring into the World, cannot be well expreſſed, it will bring back the Golden Age, and preſently put a new Face on all Affairs; it will joyn Juſtice and Mercy, Truth and Peace together, in ſuch an inſeparable Bond, that all the Malice and Subtilty of the Grand Impoſtor (who is now going to his Priſon) ſhall not be able to unlooſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">Firſt, The Man of Sin will be pulled down, and we ſhall hear no more of the Bloody Machinations of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Cruelty of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Inquiſition, the Barbarity of <hi>French</hi> or <hi>Iriſh</hi> Maſſacres, nor of the Unnaturalneſs of <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Rebellions, no Holy Leagues or Solemn Leagues and Covenants, or Aſſociations, will be heard of amongſt us; but <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> from an <hi>Aceldama,</hi> will be made like the Garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> or Paradice of <hi>God;</hi>
                  </q> 
                  <hi>and every Nation have its Tree of Life, or Fountain of Living Water in the middle, which by its constans Irrignous Streams, will cool all Heart and Animoſities, and bring all in Subjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the Gentle Laws of the Holy Jeſus:</hi> 
                  <q rend="margQuotes">But further, We ſhall hear of no Plots or Contrivances, or Black and Bloody Charges and Miſrepreſentations, all Noiſe of Perſecution or flying for Religion, the Proreſtants from <hi>France,</hi> or Papiſts from <hi>England,</hi> will ceaſe; no Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick to be Burned, or Schiſmatick to be Ruined; and the reaſon is, becauſe <hi>all Law,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> and <hi>Parties, Names</hi> of <hi>Diſtinctions,</hi> and all other Cauſes and Curſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52247:22"/>Motives of Miſchief and Diſtraction will be utterly Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd, and caſt into the ſame Dungeon with the great Criminal and Deviſer of them. But my Contemplation ſtill carries me further, in Congratulation of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of <hi>Christendom</hi> on this Alteration; How eaſy muſt be their Government, and how happy their Days, when the heavy Eccleſiaſtical Yoke is taken from their Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders? When they may be ſerved by <hi>all</hi> their Subjects, when they may puniſh <hi>ſingle</hi> Offenders, and not offend whole Parties, when there are no Parties to be pleaſed or diſpleaſed, and none to be Inflamed againſt the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by diſcontented States-men? And ſince ſome will be Lords, keep the Power to oppreſs, and give no Tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to men of differing Thoughts and Apprehenſions, This method will ſet them on a level with their Brethren, <hi>and there will be no need that Toleration ſhould be either gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or taken;</hi> and Then they may reckon their Crowns to ſet much ſurer on their Heads, when none have a priviledge or pretence to offend on the Score of a <hi>Tender Conſcience:</hi>
                  </q> But in a more particular manner, as to our own Nation and preſent Circumſtances, a conſiderable body of us are for a Church of <hi>England,</hi> a Religion Eſtabliſhed by a Law, for Biſhops, for Eccleſiaſtical Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Conformity, and a National Church; others we have who are a no leſs conſiderable body, which we call <hi>Diſſenters</hi> (though indeed all are Diſſenters one from another) and theſe would have no Biſhops, no Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Government, or Lordſhips, or Temporal Dignities conferred on Spiritual Men, and no Superiority of Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, but would have Paſtors, and Elders, and Deacons; <hi>and in ſhort,</hi> another differing way of Adminiſtration. Again, The firſt, which we call <hi>Church-men,</hi> and the others which we call <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> are divided and ſub-divided, and have ſeveral Denominations and Claſſes, and Diſtinctions amongſt themſelves; one are for Moderation and Condeſcention; another for
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:52247:22"/>Strictneſs, and the <hi>Bigotted</hi> to their Law and Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some again are for a <hi>National,</hi> ſome for a <hi>Synodical,</hi> and others an <hi>Independant</hi> Church; ſome draw one way, and ſome another, and all would have their own <hi>little.</hi> Way and Method prevail, ſo that we are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly Diſtracted and Confounded, and can come to no Settlement or Agreement, only we all agree in this, to call our ſelves by one general Name; and that is <hi>not</hi> Chriſtian, but <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> We all proteſt againſt <hi>Popery,</hi> a Name for <hi>another ſort of Chriſtians,</hi> which poſſeſs ſeveral Kingdoms and Nations, which we call our <hi>common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</hi> Now</p>
               <p>Was but theſe <hi>Angeli Evangelizantes,</hi> theſe Goſpel An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels or Miniſters of the Goſpel, inſtituted and appointed in each Nation as afore-ſaid, to go their Stages and Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuits:</p>
               <p>Firſt, As I ſaid before, we ſhould have <hi>no Popery,</hi> and by conſequence <hi>no Proteſtants</hi> to Proteſt againſt it; and all our Names of Diſtinction ſo deſtructive to our ſelves, when caſt into ſuch an <hi>Avarage,</hi> would be perfectly loſt; we ſhould have no Contentions for Offices, Dignities, or Superiority, the Lot would give an equal Title and Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to all. Hitherto the Miniſters of the Goſpel has been appointed by <hi>Men,</hi> ſo has been corrupted and forced to ſerve the ends of Princes, of ſeveral Parties; and ill-deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Polititians, Has been mixt with all our Governments, and clog'd with <hi>Humane Inventions</hi> and <hi>Traditions;</hi> but by <hi>This</hi> Method <hi>God Himſelf</hi> would chooſe his Miniſters: and then from <hi>Humane</hi> and <hi>Earthly,</hi> it would preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Heavenly</hi> and <hi>Divine;</hi> all the Siniſter Arts to get Church Preferment (ſo deſtructive to publick Peace and Truth) would fall to the Ground; the Doctors would ceaſe to Flatter the Court to get Biſhop-Pricks; and Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cturers, their Pariſhoners or Patrons to advance their Sti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend; it would be put out of the Power of Ignorant Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons to prefer Ignorant Novices to the Miniſtry, or Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:52247:23"/>Parents a weak and unfit Boy for the Univerſity; <hi>Nay, it would be put out of the Power of Princes and States themſelves to give Preferment, or make Miniſters,</hi> and ſo by conſequence (as they have but too much done) <hi>to make what Goſpel they pleaſe.</hi> And we may reaſonably hope, that Truth will then be a Virgin, and appear in her Native Beauty, when Honours, Lordſhips, and great Revenues, the common Temptations to Deflower and Diſguiſe her, are taken away, and it will not a little contribute to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Peace, when all <hi>Denials,</hi> the common Parent of <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content</hi> are removed; But what may be as great an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducement as any to move a Complyance hereto by all our Sides and Parties, is, <hi>That whereas they would all have their own ways to be preferred, This Method will make no Party ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upper or under, but will pull all in general down, and ſet none in particular up, ſo will prevent all Emulation, and give none of them reaſon to Complain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From what hath been ſaid, it may reaſonably be expected, that the perplexed Nations of Chriſtendom ſhould hearken to ſo excellent an Occonomy, eſpecially the <hi>ſettleing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triots</hi> of our own diſtracted Nations; and in hearkening to it, they will but hearken to the plain Precept and Advice of their Bleſſed Lord and great Legiſlator. For his Words are theſe, <hi>All Power is given me in Heaven and Earth, go ye therefore and Teach all Nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, of the Son, and of the Holy Choſt; Teaching them to Obſerve all things whatſoever I have commanded you; and lo I am with you always even to the END of the World.</hi> As if he had ſaid, May be ſome may queſtion your Power and Authority to Preach my Golpel; or 'tis poſſible you your ſelves may think my Commiſſion not ſufficient, but expect to receive your Power and Commiſſion from the Princes of the Earth; But I tell you it is <hi>ſufficient,</hi> and that I have Received all Power, both in Heaven and Earth, <hi>Go ye therefore and Teach all Nations, &amp;c.</hi> In which Words our Bleſſed Lord doth ſeem plainly to Dictate to the whole
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:52247:23"/>World, how he would have his Goſpel diſpenſed; and that in every minute Circumſtance, <hi>viz.</hi> Firſt, The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, they muſt <hi>go and Teach,</hi> which doth plainly imply an <hi>Itineration;</hi> then <hi>whom,</hi> they muſt Teach <hi>all Nations.</hi> Secondly, The Duty of theſe Predicants in the <hi>matter,</hi> what they muſt do, <hi>Baptize and Teach them to Obſerve all the Things he has Commanded. And lo I am with you always even to the End of the World.</hi> This plainly implies the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation,</hi> how long he would have this Method conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, <hi>viz.</hi> for ever, to the <hi>End</hi> of the World; and is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a promiſe of a Bleſſing on the due performance thereof. But here let me Note, that the Princes of the Earth, though <hi>Idolatrous</hi> and <hi>Pagan,</hi> had all the right and legal Power <hi>in ordinary;</hi> and that both our Saviour ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, and the Apoſtles well knew, but not being Proſelyted to his Doctrine, would grant no Commiſſions, or Authoriſe ſuch Preachers; therefore he himſelf, as well as they, had Power on Earth (yea all Power in an Extraordinary manner) was fain to uſe it, and iſſue out the firſt Commiſſions; but the Nature and Intent of theſe Commiſſions was not to convey a Power to a ſort of men <hi>distinct</hi> from the State, but was an Act of Neceſſity; and he had not uſed any Power, or given his Commiſſions at all, if the High Prieſt or Jewiſh Sanhedrim would have done it. The Princes and States of Chriſtendom therefore ſince ſufficiently Proſelyted to the Faith of Jeſus; may juſtly iſſue out their <hi>Que Warranto's</hi> againſt all Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Power, and all Perſons whatſoever, who claim any Power, Priviledge, or Juriſdiction <hi>jure divino,</hi> diſtinct from theirs, for it peculiarly belongs to them as Nurſing Fathers of the Church, to iſſue out their Commiſſions, and to ſay, <hi>Go and Teach, &amp;c.</hi> 'Tis true, if they ſend none, or ſend thoſe that are contrary to Chriſts Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which inſtead of giving the Children Bread, will give them Stones; then the Power Lapſes, and returns to its Fountain, and Men muſt Act by vertue of Chriſts
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:52247:24"/>Extraordinary Commiſſion, and have recourſe to his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Power, For Chriſt muſt be Preached. <hi>Princes</hi> ought to have the Preference; but if they neglect their <hi>Duty,</hi> Renounce their <hi>Power,</hi> or are ſo far from command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, that they forbid it; Then <hi>God muſt be Obeyed, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than Man;</hi> as has been the Plea (and a juſt one too) of all hitherto that have entered on the Function. But further, I deſire to take notice of one thing more, and that is of the laſt Clauſe of our Saviour's Precept, <hi>viz. And lo I am with you always, even to the end of the World.</hi> Chriſt ſaid, <hi>his</hi> Words were Spirit and Life; but ſome there are who too much incline to the Letter, and like the old <hi>Jews,</hi> think the Kingdom of Heaven ſhould come with Obſervation. They expect a <hi>new</hi> Material Heaven and a new Earth; and that Chriſt will come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain on Earth perſonally, and Reign a <hi>Thouſand Years</hi> in great Glory: Thoſe are but Fancies, for the Text ſeems to be plain, And <hi>lo I am with you always, even to the End of the World.</hi> Firſt, this plainly implies, the World ſhall have an end, and then his Willingneſs, that this way of Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration ſhould continue <hi>ſo long;</hi> and he mentions not the leaſt word of his coming again in the Interim, or that the world ſhall have <hi>Two Ends;</hi> which now leaving the world we may reaſonably ſuppoſe he would have made ſome mention of, if ſuch things ſhould have come to paſs. It ſeems plainly to me therefore, that there will be no New <hi>Material</hi> Heaven or Earth, or that Chriſt will come Perſonally again to Reign amongſt Men, and my Reaſon is, his own Words, <hi>Lo I am with you always, even to the End of the World;</hi> not <hi>I will be,</hi> but <hi>I am</hi> with you; and what he promiſed them, was not a <hi>Perſonal,</hi> but a <hi>Miniſterial Preſence:</hi> A Preſence by his Spirit; as if he had ſaid, If you will go and continue to Preach my Goſpel amongſt all Nations. I promiſe to Aid you in your Adminiſtration, and Aſſiſt you by the Influence of my Spirit, and that not for a <hi>little</hi> Time, but to the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:52247:24"/>
                  <hi>end</hi> of the World; which Promiſe he performed, and and that in a ſpecial Manner; ſo long as they continued to obſerve his Words and Inſtitution. But when Men began to make <hi>Merchandize</hi> of his Goſpel, to Monopolize and to Cloſet up the Sun-Beams, and to put their Candle under a Buſhel; no wonder they fell into ſuch Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Confuſion, and no wonder he withdrew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and the preſence of his Spirit from them. If therefore, we expect his coming again, or his more <hi>particular Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> in the large Effuſions of his Spirit, We muſt ſend forth his Light and his Truth, and ceaſe to Sell and parcel out his Goſpel: we muſt draw it out of the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons in which particular Parties have impriſoned it, and ſet it on a <hi>Candlestick,</hi> on a Mountain, that it may be as free as the <hi>Air</hi> or the <hi>Sun-beams:</hi> It has been long <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaved</hi> and <hi>Enthrall'd;</hi> and if we a little view the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> and conſider what <hi>Canons, Conſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Decretals,</hi> what differing <hi>Cuſtoms, Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> and <hi>Prejudices</hi> there are, how many differing <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions,</hi> and differing <hi>Intereſts;</hi> the multitude of <hi>Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies</hi> and <hi>Traditions,</hi> the various Forms of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Scenes</hi> of <hi>Government;</hi> and how fond every Nation and Party; nay, every individual Man, is of his own Way: It will ſeem a very difficult Thing, to Extricate and free it from ſo great a <hi>Bondage;</hi> but the greater the <hi>Work,</hi> the more worthy the <hi>Author,</hi> and more <hi>Glory</hi> to God. <hi>Pharoah</hi> kept the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> long in <hi>Bondage,</hi> and was loth to let them go, reaping great <hi>Advantages</hi> by them, as ſome do by the Goſpel: But when <hi>the God of Heaven</hi> called for, and demanded them, he was forced to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore him his <hi>Heritage</hi> and his <hi>Choſen.</hi> Chriſt is now <hi>calling</hi> for his Goſpel and his Saints; and God for <hi>his Jews,</hi> his antient <hi>People</hi> and <hi>Inheritance;</hi> and <hi>They</hi> will ſhake the <hi>Heavens</hi> and <hi>Earth,</hi> but they will have them. <hi>For by Fire and by Sword will they plead with all Fleſh,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:52247:25"/>and the Slain of the Lord ſhall be many.</hi> The <hi>God of Pleaven</hi> has already begun to ſhake the <hi>Nations</hi> and is about to fulfil all his <hi>Promiſes</hi> made to the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles</hi> by the Mouth of all his <hi>Prophets. Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66 and the 12. <hi>I will extend Peace to her like a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and the Glory of the Gentiles like a flowing Stream.</hi> Now what can be liker to a flowing Stream, than theſe <hi>Angeli Evangelizantes?</hi> Theſe <hi>Goſpel Angels,</hi> which by a conſtant Flux and Reflux from the Heart of each Nation, <hi>will fill the Earth full of the Knowledge of the Lord, as the Waters cover the Sea; No dry or barren Corners ſhall eſcape watering from theſe Fountains, and no dark Receſſes the Rays of their Light.</hi> But Poor <hi>Homuncio,</hi> I fall under the Weight, being not able to deſcribe the <hi>Advantages</hi> of this <hi>Oeconomie;</hi> I muſt again call the <hi>Prophet</hi> to my Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance in that Pathetick Deſcription of this <hi>Temple of Peace,</hi> this new <hi>Jeruſalem, cap.</hi> 65. <hi>ver.</hi> 17. <hi>For behold, I create a New Heavens, and a New Earth, and the former ſhall not be remembred, or come into mind; But be you glad and rejoyce for ever in that which I Create: For behold, I create.</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>a Rejoycing, and her People a Joy; And I will rejoyce in</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and Joy in my People; and the Voice of Weeping, ſhall be no more heard in her nor the Voice of crying. There ſhall be no more thence an Infant of Days, nor an old Man that hath not filled his Days: For the Child ſhall die an hundred Years old, but the Sinner being an hundred Years old, ſhall be Accurſed: And they ſhall build Houſes, and inhabit them; and they ſhall plant Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards, and eat the Fruit of them. They ſhall not Build, and another Inhabit; they ſhall not Plant, and another Eat. For as the days of a Tree are the days of my People, and mine Elect ſhall long enjoy the Work of their Hands: They ſhall not labour in Vain, nor bring forth for Trouble: For they are the Seed of the Bleſſed of the Lord, and their Off<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpring with them. And it ſhall come to paſs, that before
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:52247:25"/>they call, I will anſwer; and whilſt they are yet ſpeaking, I will hear. The Wolf and the Lamb ſhall feed together, and the Lion ſhall eat Straw like the Bullock; and Dust ſhall be the Serpent</hi>'s <hi>Meat. They ſhall not hurt, or destroy in all my Holy Mountain, ſaith the Lord.</hi> It ſhall come to paſs <hi>ſo</hi> and <hi>ſo,</hi> ſay the Prophets; but as yet ſuch things have <hi>not</hi> come to paſs: But this Adminiſtration of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of the <hi>holy Jeſus,</hi> not my <hi>own,</hi> but founded on Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Writ, will bring ſuch things to paſs. it will by its ſweet and gentle Influences, ſoften and mollifie the Rug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedneſs of the World, appeaſe the Heavens, and trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Earth, and render it a Paradiſe, it will ſet Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Truth and Peace, on an unmoveable Foundation; and turn the <hi>World</hi> in a manner into a <hi>Theocracy.</hi> For 'tis more than probable, that by degrees it will vacate and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſede all <hi>humane Sanctions,</hi> and make them of little Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, by its prevailing Energy and pacifick Nature; making <hi>Love,</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Condeſcenſion,</hi> the Principal Rulers of the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe.</hi> Then will the God of <hi>Love,</hi> or <hi>Truth,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> viſit us, and make his abode with us, and rain down his Bleſſing and Graces upon us, as at the Beginning; and we ſhall become a <hi>Royal Priecthood,</hi> a <hi>Peculiar People,</hi> zealous (not of deſtroying one another, <hi>as at this Day</hi>) but zealous of good <hi>Works. Ephraim</hi> ſhall no more vex <hi>Judah,</hi> nor <hi>Judah Ephraim</hi> Every Prince and Nation ſhall be content with their own Territory and Borders: The noiſe of <hi>War</hi> ſhall no more be heard of amongſt us, our Swords ſhall be turned into <hi>Plow Shares,</hi> and our Spears into <hi>Pruning Hooks. Zech.</hi> 2 verſ. 10. <hi>Sing and Rejoyce, O Daughter or</hi> Sion, <hi>for lo I come and will dwell in the</hi> midſt <hi>of thee, ſaith the Lord; And many Nations ſhall be joyned to the Lord in that day, and ſhall be my People; and I will dwell in the</hi> midſt of <hi>thee; and thou ſhalt know that the Lord of Hoſts hath ſent me unto thee; and the Lord ſhall inherit</hi> Judah, <hi>his Portion in the Holy Land, and chooſe</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>again.</hi> Be ſilent O all
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:52247:26"/>Fleſh before the Lord, for he is raiſed up out of his Holy Habitation. <hi>And it ſhall be in that day, that</hi> Living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>ſhall go out from</hi> Jeruſalem; <hi>half of them,</hi> (viz. Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers) <hi>towards the former Sea, and half of them towards the hinder Sea; in Summer and in Winter ſhall it be. And the Lord ſhall be King over all the Earth; In that day ſhall there be</hi> One <hi>Lord, and his Name</hi> One: <hi>The</hi> Jews <hi>and the</hi> Gentiles <hi>ſhall uſe the ſame Method and Way of Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſend out their Preachers from the</hi> midſt <hi>of their Habitations.</hi> But the Queſtion will be asked, how all the preſent Difficulties will be ſurmounted? In anſwer to which, let the ſame Prophet ſpeak, <hi>Who art thou, O great Mountain? Before</hi> Zerubbabel (Chriſt) <hi>Thou ſhalt become a Plain; and he ſhall bring forth the</hi> Head Stone <hi>there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with ſhouting, crying,</hi> Grace, Grace. <hi>The Hands of</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>have laid the Foundation of this Houſe, his Hands ſhall alſo finiſh it. And thou ſhalt know, that the Lord of Hoſts hath ſent me unto you.</hi> Chriſt is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt, the Conſideration of which, brings me to my Concluſion; in which I ſhall vindicate my ſelf from the Charge of Innovation, and ſay,</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">The way which I propoſe, is not a new Way, but the <hi>Renovation</hi> of an old One: For 'tis the way by which Chriſtianity <hi>Entred</hi> the World; and therefore the moſt likely to <hi>preſerve</hi> it; 'tis the way which the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> uſed, which our <hi>Saviour</hi> practiſed; he went up and down doing Good, he ſent out the <hi>Twelve,</hi> and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venty <hi>Diſciples;</hi> who Preached his Goſpel through the <hi>Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> and then returned to him again. When he was leaving the Earth, by a plain Indigitation, he Recommended this way. 'Tis a way pregnant with all the Felicities can be imagined; 'tis advantageous to all Governments, and friendly to all Societies; 'twill bring <hi>Glory</hi> to God on High, reſtore <hi>Peace</hi> on Earth, and <hi>good Will</hi> amongſt Men.</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:52247:26"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <q>How Beautiful upon the Mountains are the Feet of him that bringeth good Tidings, that publiſheth Peace, that bringeth good Tidings of good, that publiſheth Salvation, that ſaith unto <hi>Zion,</hi> Thy God Reigneth! <bibl>Iſa. 52. Verſe 7.</bibl>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>
                  <hi>Haec cùm fiunt, &amp; Statu hoc, Harmonium &amp; Pacem adfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rente, inter Gentiles in Terris Chriſtianis poſito, mirabuntur Judaei, Christoque Authori Auſpicatiſſimo tum demùm credent. Nec non, pacato Deo, vocante, Christiano adjuvante, magno cum gaudio &amp; Triumpho, poſt tam longum ob malitiam &amp; incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulitatem exulatum, ad ſuas Terras Hieroſolymitanas, ex omnibus plagis &amp; Terrarum Regionibus redibunt: Nec futilia aut inania Antiquorum Prophetarum Vaticinia de faelici</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeorum <hi>aut Gentilium Statut, diutiùs habebuntur. Nam omnia iſta Grandiloquia, de</hi> Pace, Juſtitiâ, &amp; Veritate, <hi>plenam Solutionem hoc Miniſterio Theocratico habebunt; &amp; exiguo Temporis Spatio, Diverſas Mundi Regiones, quaſi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſas unius gentis Civitates, mutuo foedere irrefragabilis ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citicae conjunctas, Spectabimus. Et Preces illa tum frequent in ore Sacerdotum,</hi> viz. Revoca ad Sedes antiquam Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Judaeorum, &amp; gloriam Gentilium redde completam, habebit reſponſum.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
